<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Here begynneth the chorle and the byrde</title>
            <title>Chorle and the birde</title>
            <author>Lydgate, John, 1370?-1451?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1510</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 20 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06546</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17012</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120581</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855777</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855777</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21279</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06546)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21279)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Here begynneth the chorle and the byrde</title>
                  <title>Chorle and the birde</title>
                  <author>Lydgate, John, 1370?-1451?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In the Flete strete in the sygne of the sonne by Wynkyn de Worde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Enprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1510?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By John Lydgate.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name and place of publication from colophon; publication date estimated by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A.</note>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>French poetry --  Translations into English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:21279:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21279:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>¶ Here begynneth the chorle and the byrde.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21279:2"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Roblemes of olde lykenes &amp; fygures.</l>
               <l>Whiche ꝓu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>n fructuoꝰ of ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tence</l>
               <l>And auct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>es grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded on ſcrypturꝭ</l>
               <l>By reſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blaunce of notable apparence</l>
               <l>with moralytes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cludy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge on prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</l>
               <l>Lyke as the nyble reherſeth by wrytynge</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>s choſe them ſomtyme a kynge</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Fyrſt in theyr choſe they named the olyue</l>
               <l>To reygne amonge them (Iudiciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) doth expreſſe</l>
               <l>But he hym ſelfe gan excuſe belyue</l>
               <l>He myght not forſake his tatreneſſe</l>
               <l>Ne the fygge tree his amerous ſwetneſſe</l>
               <l>Ne the vyne his holſome tarage</l>
               <l>Whiche gyueth comforte to all maner aege</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſemblably poetes laurente</l>
               <l>By derke parables full conuenyent</l>
               <l>Fayne that byrdes and beeſtes of eſtate</l>
               <l>As ryall egles and lyons by aſſente</l>
               <l>Sente out wryttes to holde a parlayment</l>
               <l>And made decrets bryefly for to ſay</l>
               <l>Some to haue lordſhyp and ſome to obeye</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Egles in the ayre hygheſt make theyr flyght</l>
               <l>Power of lyons on the grounde is ſene</l>
               <l>Cedre amonge trees hygheſt is of ſyght</l>
               <l>And the laurere of nature is aye grene</l>
               <l>Of floures all Flora aye goddeſſe and quene</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21279:2"/>
               <l>Thus of all thynges there ben dyuerſytees</l>
               <l>Some of eſtate and ſome of lowe degrees</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Poetes wryte wonderfull lyknes</l>
               <l>And vnder couerte kepe them ſelfe cloſe</l>
               <l>They take beeſtes and foules to wytnes</l>
               <l>Of whoſe faynynge fables fyrſt aroſe</l>
               <l>And here I call to my purpoſe</l>
               <l>Out of frenſſhe a tale to tranſlate</l>
               <l>Whiche in a paunflete I redde and ſawe late</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This tale whiche I make of mencyon</l>
               <l>In groos reherſed playnly to declare</l>
               <l>Thre prouerbes payed for a raunſon</l>
               <l>Of a byrde whiche was take in a ſnare</l>
               <l>Wonder deſyrous to ſcape fro her care</l>
               <l>Of myn auctours folowynge the proceſſe</l>
               <l>So as it befell in order I ſhall expreſſe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Somtyme there was a ſmall vyllage</l>
               <l>As myn auctour maketh rehercayle</l>
               <l>A chorle whiche had luſte and grete courage</l>
               <l>Within hymſelfe by delygent trauayle</l>
               <l>To make a gardyn of ryche entayle</l>
               <l>Of length and brede lyke ſquare and longe</l>
               <l>Hedged and dytched to make it ſure &amp; ſtronge</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All the aleys were made playne with ſonde</l>
               <l>The benche couered with newe turues grene Chorle.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21279:3"/>
               <l>Swete herbe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s with conduytes at the honde</l>
               <l>That wyll it vp agayne the ſonne ſhene</l>
               <l>Lyke ſyluer ſtremes as cryſtall clene</l>
               <l>The burbyll wayes in theyr vp boylynge</l>
               <l>Rounde as beryll the bemes out ſhewynge</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Mydde in the gardyn ſtode a freſſhe lauryre</l>
               <l>Theron a byrde ſyngynge daye and nyght</l>
               <l>With ſhynynge fethers bryghter than golde wyre</l>
               <l>Whiche with her ſonge made heuy hertes lyght</l>
               <l>That to beholde it was an heuenly ſyght</l>
               <l>How towarde euen and in the dawenynge</l>
               <l>She dyde her payne mooſt amerouſly to ſynge</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Eſperus enforced ſtrongely her courage</l>
               <l>Towarde euen whan Phebus gan to weſt</l>
               <l>Amonge the braunches to her auauntage</l>
               <l>To ſynge her complyne and than go to reſt</l>
               <l>And at ryſynge of quene Alceſte</l>
               <l>To ſynge agayne as it was her dewe</l>
               <l>Erly on morowe the daye ſterre to ſalewe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It was a very heuenly melodye</l>
               <l>Euen and morne to here the byrdes ſonge</l>
               <l>And the ſwete ſugred armonye</l>
               <l>Of vncoute werblys and tewnes drawe alonge</l>
               <l>That all the gardyn of the noyſe ronge</l>
               <l>Tyll on morowe whan Tytan ſhone clere</l>
               <l>This byrde was trapped &amp; caught with a pantere</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21279:3"/>
            <lg>
               <l>The chorle was glad whan he this byrde had take</l>
               <l>Mery of chere of loke and of vyſage</l>
               <l>And in all haſte he purpoſed to make</l>
               <l>Within his houſe a lytell preaty cage</l>
               <l>And with her ſonge to reioyſe his courage</l>
               <l>Tyll at the laſte the ſely byrde abrayd</l>
               <l>And ſoberly thus to the chorle ſhe ſayd</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I am nowe take and ſtande vnder dangere</l>
               <l>Holden ſtreyght that I may not flee</l>
               <l>A dieu my ſonge and all my notes clere</l>
               <l>Nowe that I haue loſte my lybertee</l>
               <l>Now am I thrall where ſomtyme I was free</l>
               <l>And truſte well whyle that I am in dyſtreſſe</l>
               <l>I can not ſynge nor make no gladneſſe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And though my cage forged were of golde</l>
               <l>And the pynacles of berell and cryſtall</l>
               <l>I remembre a prouerbe ſayd of olde</l>
               <l>Who leſeth his fredome forſoth he leſeth all</l>
               <l>For I had leuer vpon a braunche ſmall</l>
               <l>Merely to ſynge amonge the wodes grene</l>
               <l>Than in a cage of ſyluer bryght and ſhene</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Songe in pryſon hath none accordaunce</l>
               <l>Troweſt thou that I wyll ſynge in pryſon</l>
               <l>Songe procedeth of Ioye and pleaſaunce.</l>
               <l>And pryſon cauſeth deth and deſtruccyon</l>
               <l>Ryngynge of feters is no mery ſowne</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21279:4"/>
               <l>Or how ſholde he be gladde or Iocounde</l>
               <l>Agayne his wyll that lyeth in chaynes bounde</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What auayleth it a lyon to be kynge</l>
               <l>Of beeſts all ſhette in a toure of ſtone</l>
               <l>Or an egle vnder ſtreyte kepynge</l>
               <l>Called alſo kynge of fowles euerychone</l>
               <l>Fye on lordſhyppe whan lyberte is gone</l>
               <l>Anſwere herto lette it not a ſterte</l>
               <l>Who ſyngeth meryly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyngeth not at herte</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And yf thou wylte reioyſe of my ſyngynge</l>
               <l>Lette me go fle ferre frome all daungere</l>
               <l>And euery daye in the mornynge</l>
               <l>I ſhall repayre vpon thy laurere</l>
               <l>And freſſhely ſynge with luſty notes clere</l>
               <l>Vnder thy chambre or afore thyne halle</l>
               <l>Euery ſeaſon whan thou lyſt me call</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To be ſhytte vp and pynned vnder drede</l>
               <l>Nothynge accordeth vnto my nature</l>
               <l>Though I were fed with mylke &amp; waſtell brede</l>
               <l>And with cruddes brought to my paſture</l>
               <l>Yet had I leuer to do my beſy cure</l>
               <l>Erly on morowe to ſcrape in the vale</l>
               <l>To fynde my dyner amonge the wormes ſmale</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The labourer is gladder at the plough</l>
               <l>Erly on morowe to feede hym on bacon</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21279:4"/>
               <l>Than ſome man is that hath good ynough</l>
               <l>And all deyntes plente and foyſon</l>
               <l>And hath no fredome with his poſſeſſyon</l>
               <l>To go at large but as a bere at a ſtake</l>
               <l>To paſſe his bondes but yf he leue take</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Take this anſwere for a full concluſyon</l>
               <l>To ſynge in pryſon y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalte not me conſtrayne</l>
               <l>Tyll I haue fredome in wodes vp and downe</l>
               <l>To flee at large on bowes rough and playne</l>
               <l>And of reaſon thou ſholdeſt not dyſdayne</l>
               <l>Of my deſyre but laughe and haue game</l>
               <l>But who is a chorle he wold eche ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Well quod the chorle ſyeth it wyll not be</l>
               <l>That I deſyre as by thy talkynge,</l>
               <l>Maugre thy wyll thou ſhalte cheſe of thre</l>
               <l>Within a cage merely to ſynge</l>
               <l>Or to the kechyne I ſhall thy body brynge</l>
               <l>Pull thy fethers that be bryght and clere</l>
               <l>And after roſt or bake the to my ſopere</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Than ſayd the byrde to reaſon ſay I not nay</l>
               <l>Touchynge my ſonge a full anſwere thou haſt</l>
               <l>And whan my fethers plucked ben awaye</l>
               <l>And my body roſted or baken in a paaſt</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalte of me haue a ſmall repaaſt</l>
               <l>But and thou wylte werke by my counceyll</l>
               <l>Thou mayſt by me haue a grete auayll</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21279:5"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Yf thou wylte to my reaſon aſſent</l>
               <l>And ſuffre me go frely frome pryſon</l>
               <l>Without raunſon or ony other rente</l>
               <l>I ſhall the ryue a notable guardon</l>
               <l>Thre grete wyſdoms accordynge to reaſon</l>
               <l>More of value take hede what I profre</l>
               <l>Than all the golde that ſhytte is in thy cofre</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Truſte me well I ſhall the not dyſceyue</l>
               <l>Well ſayd the chorle tell anone lette ſe</l>
               <l>Nay ſayd the byrde thou muſt afore conceyue</l>
               <l>Who ſhall teche of reaſon muſt go fre</l>
               <l>It ſytteth a mayſter to haue his lyberte</l>
               <l>And at large to teche his leſſon</l>
               <l>Haue me not ſuſpecte I meane no treaſon</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Well ſayd the chorle I holde me contente</l>
               <l>I truſte thy promyſe that thou haſt made to me</l>
               <l>The byrde flewe forth the chorle was of aſſent</l>
               <l>And toke her flyght vpon the laurer tree</l>
               <l>Than thought ſhe thus nowe ſtande I free</l>
               <l>With ſnares &amp; panters I purpoſe not my lyue</l>
               <l>Ne with no lyme twygges ony more to ſtryue</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He is a fole that ſcaped is fro daungere</l>
               <l>And hath broke his feters &amp; fledde out of pryſon</l>
               <l>Agayne to reſorte / brent chylde dredeth fyre</l>
               <l>Eche man beware by wyſdome and reaſon</l>
               <l>Suger ſtrawed that hydeth falſe poyſon</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21279:5"/>
               <l>There is no venym ſo peryllous of ſharpneſſe</l>
               <l>As whan it hath of tryacle the lykeneſſe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Who dredeth no peryll in peryll he ſhall falle</l>
               <l>Smoth waters ben oftyme depe</l>
               <l>The quayle pype can mooſt falſly calle</l>
               <l>Tyll the quayle vnder the nette doth crepe</l>
               <l>A blere eyed fowler truſte not though he wepe</l>
               <l>Eſchewe his thombe of wepynge take none hede</l>
               <l>That ſmale byrde can nype by the hede</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And now that I ſuche daungere am eſchaped</l>
               <l>Ilwyll beware and for a prouyde</l>
               <l>That of no fowler I wyll no more be Iaped</l>
               <l>Fro theyr lyme twygges I wyll flee fer a ſyde</l>
               <l>Where peryll is peryll is to abyde</l>
               <l>Come nere thou chorle and herke to my ſpeche</l>
               <l>Of thre wyſedomes that I ſhall the teche</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Neue not of wyſedome to haſtely credence</l>
               <l>To euery tale ne to euery tydynge</l>
               <l>But conceyue of reaſon and of prudence</l>
               <l>Amonge many tales in many a leſynge</l>
               <l>Haſtely credence hath cauſed grete hyndrynge</l>
               <l>Reporte of tales and tydynges tolde of newe</l>
               <l>Maketh many a man to beholde vntrewe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For one parte take this for my raunſon</l>
               <l>Lerne the ſeconde grounded on ſcrypture</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21279:6"/>
               <l>Deſyre not thou by no condycyon</l>
               <l>Thynge whiche is Impoſſyble to recure</l>
               <l>Worldly deſyres ſtonde all in auenture</l>
               <l>And who deſyreth to clymbe hyghe a lofte</l>
               <l>By ſodayne tourne falleth ofte vnſofte</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The thyrde is this beware bothe eue and morowe</l>
               <l>Forgete it not but lerne this of me</l>
               <l>For treaſour loſt make neuer to grete ſorowe</l>
               <l>Whiche in no wyſe may recouered be</l>
               <l>For who ſoroweth for loſſe in that degre</l>
               <l>Reken fyrſt his loſſe and after his payne</l>
               <l>Of one ſorowe he maketh ſorowes twayne</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>After this leſſon the byrde began a ſonge</l>
               <l>Of her eſcape gretely reioyſynge</l>
               <l>And remembred her alſo of the wronge</l>
               <l>Done by the chorle fyrſt at her takynge</l>
               <l>Of her affraye and of her pryſonynge</l>
               <l>Glad that ſhe was at large and out of drede</l>
               <l>Sayd to hym houynge aboue his heed</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou were ſayd ſhe a very naturell fole</l>
               <l>To ſuffre me departe of thy lewdnes</l>
               <l>Thou oughtes of ryght complayne &amp; make dole</l>
               <l>And in thyn herte to haue grete heuynes</l>
               <l>That thou haſt loſt ſo paſſynge grete ryches</l>
               <l>Whiche myght ſuffyſe by value in rekenynge</l>
               <l>To paye the raunſon of a myghty kynge</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21279:6"/>
            <lg>
               <l>There is a ſtone whiche called is a Iagonce</l>
               <l>Of olde engendred within myn entrayll</l>
               <l>Whiche of fyne golde peyſeth an vnce</l>
               <l>Cytryne of colour lyke garnettes of entayll</l>
               <l>Whiche maketh men vyctoryous in batayll</l>
               <l>And who ſo euer bere on hym the ſtone</l>
               <l>Is full aſſured agaynſt his mortall fone</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Who hath this ſtone in his poſſeſſyon</l>
               <l>Shall ſuffre no pouerte no none Indygence</l>
               <l>But of all treſour haue plente and foyſon</l>
               <l>And euery man ſhall do hym reuerence</l>
               <l>And enemye ſhall do hym none offence</l>
               <l>But frome thyn hondes now that I am gone</l>
               <l>Playne yf thou wylte for thy parte is none</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It cauſeth loue it maketh men gracyous</l>
               <l>And fauourable in euery mannes ſyght</l>
               <l>It maketh accorde bytwene folkes enuyous</l>
               <l>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forteth ſorowfull maketh heuy hertes lyght</l>
               <l>Lyke to paſyon of colour ſonnyſſhe bryght</l>
               <l>I am a fole to tell all at ones</l>
               <l>Or teche a chorle the pryſe of precyous ſtones</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Men ſholde not put a precyous margaryte</l>
               <l>As rubyes ſaphyres and other ſtones of ynde</l>
               <l>Emerawdes and other perles whyte</l>
               <l>Afore rude ſwyne that loue drafe of kynde</l>
               <l>For a ſowe delyteth as I fynde</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21279:7"/>
               <l>More in draffe her pygges for to glade</l>
               <l>Than in all the perry that cometh out of garnade</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Eche thynge draweth to his ſemblable</l>
               <l>Fyſſhes in the ſee Beſtes on the ſtronde</l>
               <l>The ayer for foules by nature is couenable</l>
               <l>And to the plough man for to tyll the londe</l>
               <l>And to a chorle a dongforke in his honde</l>
               <l>I leſe my tyme ony more to tary</l>
               <l>For to tell a chorle of lapydary</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That thou haddeſt thou getteſt nomore agayne</l>
               <l>Thy lyme twygges and panters I defye</l>
               <l>To lette me go thou were foule ouer ſene</l>
               <l>To leſe thy rycheſſe only of folye</l>
               <l>I am nowe fre to ſynge and to flye</l>
               <l>Where that me lyſte and he is a fole at all</l>
               <l>That is at large and maketh hymſelfe thrall</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To here of wyſdome thyne eeres ben halfe deef</l>
               <l>Lyke an aſſe that lyſtneth on an harpe</l>
               <l>Thou mayſt go pype on an yue leef</l>
               <l>Better is to me to ſynge on thornes ſharpe</l>
               <l>Than in a cage with a chorle to carpe</l>
               <l>For it was ſayd of folkes yeres agone</l>
               <l>A chorles chorle is ofte woo begone</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The chorle felte his herte parte on tweyne</l>
               <l>For very ſorowe and a ſonder ryue</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21279:7"/>
               <l>Alas ſayd he I may well wepe and playne</l>
               <l>As a wratche neuer lyke to thryue</l>
               <l>But for to endure in pouerte all my lyue</l>
               <l>For of foly and of wylfulnes</l>
               <l>I haue now loſte all hole my ryches</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I was a lorde I crye out on fortune</l>
               <l>I had grete traſoure late in my kepynge</l>
               <l>Whiche myght haue made me longe contynue</l>
               <l>With that ſtone to haue lyued lyke a kynge</l>
               <l>yf I had ſette it in a rynge</l>
               <l>Borne it vpon me. I had good ynoughe</l>
               <l>I ſholde than no more haue gone to the ploughe</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whan the byrde ſawe the chorle thus morne</l>
               <l>And how that he was heuy of his chere</l>
               <l>She toke her flyght and gan agayne retorne</l>
               <l>Towarde hym and ſayd as ye ſhall here</l>
               <l>O dulle chorle wyſedomes for to lere</l>
               <l>That I the taught all is lefte behynde</l>
               <l>Racyd awaye and clene out of thy mynde</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Taught I the not this wyſedome in ſentence</l>
               <l>To euery tale brought to the of newe</l>
               <l>Not to haſtely gyue therto credence</l>
               <l>Vnto tyme thou knowe that it were trewe</l>
               <l>All is not golde that ſheweth goldeſſhe hew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Nor ſtones all be nature as I fynde</l>
               <l>Be not ſaphyrs that ſhewe colour ynde</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:21279:8"/>
            <lg>
               <l>In this doctryne I loſt my labour</l>
               <l>To teche the ſuche prouerbes of ſuſtaunce</l>
               <l>Now may thou ſee thy blynde errour</l>
               <l>For all my body poyſed in balaunce</l>
               <l>Weyth not an vnce rude is thy remembraunce</l>
               <l>I to haue more poyſe cloyſed in myn entrayll</l>
               <l>Than all my body ſette for the counteruayll</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All my body weyth not an vnce</l>
               <l>How myght than I in me haue a ſtone</l>
               <l>That peyſeth more than a Iagonce</l>
               <l>Thy brayne is dulle thy wytte is almooſt gone</l>
               <l>Of thre wyſdomes thou haſt forgoten one</l>
               <l>Thou ſholdeſt not after my ſentence</l>
               <l>To euery tale to haſtely gyue credence</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I bad alſo beware bothe euen and morowe</l>
               <l>For a thynge loſte of ſodayne auenture</l>
               <l>Thou ſholdeſt not make to moche ſorowe</l>
               <l>Whan thou ſeeſt thou mayſt not it recure</l>
               <l>And here thou fayleſt whiche dooſt thy curs</l>
               <l>In thy ſnare to catche me agayne</l>
               <l>Thou arte a fole thy laboure is in vayne</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In the thyrde thou dooſt craue</l>
               <l>I bad thou ſholdeſt in no maner wyſe</l>
               <l>Coueyte thynge that thou mayſt not haue</l>
               <l>In whiche thou haſt forgone myne enpryſe</l>
               <l>Than may I ſay playnly to deuyſe</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21279:8"/>
               <l>Thou haſt of madnes forgoten all thre</l>
               <l>Notable wyſdomes that I taught the</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The vyntener treateth of holſom wynes</l>
               <l>Of gentyll fruyte boſteth the gardyner</l>
               <l>The fyſſher caſteth out hokes and lynes</l>
               <l>To catche fyſſhe in euery freſſhe ryuer</l>
               <l>Of tylthe of londe treateth the bouer</l>
               <l>The gentylman talketh of gentery</l>
               <l>The chorle delyteth to ſpeke of rybaudry</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All one to the fawcone and a kyte</l>
               <l>As good an owle as a popyngaye</l>
               <l>A ducke of the donghylle as deynte as a ſnyte</l>
               <l>Who ſerueth a chorle hath many a carefull daye</l>
               <l>A deu ſyr chorle fayre well I fle my waye</l>
               <l>I caſt me neuer hens forth my lyuynge</l>
               <l>To fore a chorle ony more to ſynge</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ye folke that ſhall this fable ſee or rede</l>
               <l>Newe forged tales I counſeyll you to fle</l>
               <l>For loſſe of good take neuer grete hede</l>
               <l>Be not ſorowfull for none aduerſyte</l>
               <l>Coueyte nothynge that may not recouered be</l>
               <l>And remembre where euerye ryde or gone</l>
               <l>A chorles chorle is alwaye woo begone</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Vnto purpoſe this prouerbe is full ryf</l>
               <l>Redde and reported by olde remembraunce</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21279:9"/>
               <l>A chyldes byrde and a knaues wyfe</l>
               <l>Haue ofte ſyth grete ſorowe and myſchaunce</l>
               <l>And who hath fredome hath all ſuffyſaunce</l>
               <l>Better is fredome with lytell in gladnes</l>
               <l>Than to be thrall with all worldely ryches</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Go lytell quayer and recommaunde me</l>
               <l>Vnto my mayſter with humbly affeccyon</l>
               <l>Beſeche hym lowly of mercy and pyte</l>
               <l>Of thy rude makynge to haue compaſſyon</l>
               <l>And as touchynge thy tranſlacyon</l>
               <l>Out of Frenſſhe / how that it Englyſſhe be</l>
               <l>All thynges is ſayd vnder correccyon</l>
               <l>With ſupportacyon of his benygnyte</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>AMEN</closer>
            <trailer>¶ Here endeth the chorle and the byrde.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Enpryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at London in the Flete ſtrete in the ſygne of the ſonne by Wynkyn de Worde.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>sign</figDesc>
                  <head>wynkyn: de: worde</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21279:9"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
